Ebenezer Foote Family Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Ebenezer Foote Family Papers 1751-1871 (bulk 1790-1807)
MSS20941
Foote, Ebenezer, 1756-1829
60 items
1 container plus 1 oversize
.2 linear feet
1 microfilm reel
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Continental Army officer, jurist, merchant, and legislator, of Delaware County, N.Y. Family and general correspondence, orders, petitions, and legal and other papers of Foote and various members of his family. Topics include the Tammany Society of New York, the death of Alexander Hamilton, the War of 1812, the incident aboard the frigate Chesapeake, the first Seminole War, and New York politics.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Foote family.; Foote, Charles Augustus, 1785-1828. Charles Augustus Foote papers.; Foote, Charles Augustus, 1818-1883. Charles Augustus Foote papers.; Foote, Ebenezer, 1756-1829.; Foote, Frederick Parsons, 1783-1827. Frederick Parsons Foote papers.; Foote, Harriet, 1773-1842. Harriet Foote papers.; Foote, Justin, 1762- Justin Foote papers.; Foote, Rensselaer, 1815-1862. Rensselaer Foote papers.; Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804--Death and burial.
Organizations
Chesapeake (Frigate); Tammany Hall (Political organization)
Subjects
Indians of North America--Wars--1815-1875.; Seminole War, 1st, 1817-1818.
Places
Delaware County (N.Y.)--History.; New York (State)--Politics and government.; United States--History--War of 1812.
Occupations
Army officers.; Judges.; Legislators--New York (State); Merchants.
Provenance
The papers of the Ebenezer Foote family, including Ebenezer Foote, Continental Army officer, jurist, merchant, and legislator, of Delaware County, N.Y., were purchased by the Library of Congress in 1943.
Additional Guides
A list of individuals referred to in the correspondence, prepared by a reference specialist some years prior to the filming of the papers, is filed at the end of Container 1 of the collection.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of the Ebenezer Foote family are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of these papers is available on one reel. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition.
Biographical Note
Ebenezer Foote
Date Event
1756 Born
1783 Left the Continental Army with the rank of major after having volunteered as a soldier at the beginning of the Revolutionary War
circa 1783 1797 In the mercantile business, Ulster County, N. Y.
1798 Appointed county clerk for the newly formed Delaware County, N.Y.
1798 1802 Member, New York State Senate, representing the Middle District
1810 1829 Judge, Ulster County, N.Y.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of the Ebenezer Foote (1756-1829) family span the years 1751-1871, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1790-1807. The collection consists of family and general correspondence, orders, petitions, and legal and other papers of Foote and various members of his family including Charles Augustus Foote (1785-1828), Charles Augustus Foote (1818-1883), Frederick Parsons Foote (1783-1827), Harriet Foote (1773-1842), Justin Foote (born 1762), and Rensselaer Foote (1815-1862). Topics include the Tammany Society of New York, the death of Alexander Hamilton, the War of 1812, the incident aboard the frigate Chesapeake in 1813, the first Seminole War, and New York politics.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is organized by type of material and therein by topic, name of person, or type of document.
Container List
Available on microfilm. Shelf no. 17,665.
- Family correspondence (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Foote, Justin, to his brother, Ebenezer Foote, 1802 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Foote, Charles (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - To his father, Ebenezer Foote, 1804, 1807 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - To his brother, Frederick Foote, 1807 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Foote, Rensselaer, to his brother, Charles Foote, 1840 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Foote, Harriet, to her nephew, Charles Foote, 1843 (Box 1, Reel 1)
- General correspondence (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - 1781-1801 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - 1809-1849 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Letter fragment, 1792 (Box 1, Reel 1)
- Miscellany (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Attorney's license, Charles Foote, 1808 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Circular letter (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - 20 Apr. 1801 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - 16 Apr. 1812 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Contract for the sale of a parcel of land, 1871 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Cover, 1799 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - General orders, Brigadier General Henry Dodge, 19 Oct. 1812 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Anonymous letter to the editor, Newburgh Packet (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Membership in the Tammany Society, 12 Mar. 1792 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Petition to the supervisors of Ulster County, 24 May 1793 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Petition to DeWitt Clinton, 16 Mar. 1825 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Shipping invoice, 29 Jan. 1802 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Copy of statement by Robert Knox concerning explosion on board the Chesapeake (frigate), 1813, during encounter with HMS Shannon (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Will of David Merritt, 15 Aug. 1751 (incomplete) See Oversize (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - A list of individuals referred to in the correspondence, prepared by a reference specialist some years prior to the filming of this collection (Box 1, Reel 1)
- Oversize (Box OV 1, Reel 1)
  - Will of David Merritt, incomplete, 15 Aug. 1751 (Container 1) (Box OV 1, Reel 1)